What's going on, everybody?
Welcome to part six of the Neural Networks
from Scratch video series.
In this video, what we're going to be
talking about in covering is the Softmax
activation function, which is specifically
used for the output layer on our
classification style neural network
models.
Before we get into that, a
quick update to the Neural
Networks from Scratch
book is now fully released.
We have a hardcover, which you see here,
as well as a softcover.
Also, the e-book now has a PDF download.
All books give you access to that PDF and
e-book, and we still also have the Google
Docs, so you can
still highlight and ask
questions in line with
the text and all that.
If you're interested in any version of the
book, you can get it at nnfs.io.
I am going to be coding everything from
the book, so you should be able to watch
the videos, read the book, and kind of cross
back and forth with very little effort.
That way, if maybe you've coded something
from the video, and then you're still
maybe a little confused, you want to get a
refresher.
You could go to the end of the video.
You could go in theory back to the book,
for example, and kind of go through the
exact same code, just in written form,
or vice versa, and so on.
So anyway, we're going to be starting off
here with the softmax activation function.
And the first question
that I'm sure many people
will have is, why another
activation function?
Why don't we just
continue to use something
like the rectified linear
activation function?
So I think to start us off, I would say,
let's just... I'm going to start with this.
..
a fresh, fresh, fresh, fresh, fresh,
fresh, fresh, fresh, fresh, fresh,
fresh.
Just for illustration purposes,
and then once we actually code the code
that we intend to continue with our...
essentially, we're building a framework here.
So for that code, we'll go back to the
code that we've been building.
But for now, we're just going to start
fresh.
So let's just say you've got some layer
outputs, and the values can be anything.
We're just going to make them up, but I
am going to use the values from the book.
4.8, 1.21, 2.385.
So imagine these are your output values.
What do we do with that?
So if we're only predicting, it's pretty
simple.
You do... you just... you
would say the prediction is
whichever one of these
values is the... is the largest.
So in this case, it would be index 0.
So let's assume index 0 is indeed the
intended target.
Awesome.
You've got your prediction right.
But what we're trying to learn how to do
is actually train neural networks as well.
So with a... you don't have to think about
this if all you're doing is predicting,
but someone had to think about it at some
point to train this model.
So if you want to train a model,
the... you know, there's a whole bunch
that goes on that we will get to and that
we'll take up many videos and many hours
of your time to figure out and learn how
this works.
But at this point, the
first step in training a
model is to determine how
wrong is this model, right?
Because accuracy is not a good indication
of that.
So for example, if we change some of these
values, maybe 4.79 and 4.25.
I don't know.
Which one of these is more correct?
Well, I think probably most people would
agree.
This first one is more correct because
relatively this neuron zero here is
relatively larger than the other neurons
in this list.
Whereas here, they're actually a lot
closer.
Accuracy wise, they're identical.
So in order to measure how
wrong something is, the first order
of business is to compare
them relatively to other neurons.
But the problem with
this is like the rectified
linear activation function,
for example, is exclusive.
It's per neuron.
They're not really connected in any way.
So there is no relative comparison that
you can really fairly make.
The next problem is these are unbounded.
So the relative closeness
can vary considerably between
each sample that you pass
through this neural network.
So we've got so many issues.
There's like a bounding issue.
Every neuron is exclusive.
They don't really relate to each other.
And we don't really have a good solid way
of determining how wrong is this in any
formal uniform way per sample that comes
through.
So this is the problem, and this is why we
need some new activation function,
which in this case we're
going to be using the
softmax activation
function to help us solve.
Now, why softmax?
Well, we need to kind of, again, kind of
consider what's our end objective here.
So zooming out to a full model for the
moment, what actually do we want to happen?
So let's say we've got some image data.
We're going to pass that through the neural
network, and then we get the output values.
Now, what do we want those values to be?
So ideally, these values would be a
probability distribution.
This gives us a few things.
First of all, this means everything will
be uniform from sample to sample.
Also, from neuron to neuron, things will
be normalized.
And we can actually calculate rightness
and wrongness, so to speak.
So in this case, the correct
classification, if everything was perfect,
the correct classification would be a 1.0,
and all the other neurons would read out
0.0.
So now we can actually begin to measure
how right or how wrong are we.
So we know this is where
we want to get, and the
question is, how do we
actually get to that point?
So one immediate idea here might be,
well, all you need to really do is
normalize the values and create that
distribution by taking each neuron's value
and divide that value by the total value
of all the neurons in that layer.
And then you're done, right?
So let's say you just use a probability
distribution, and you keep old,
faithful, rectified linear activation
function.
The problem here is if any of those values
in the output layer is a negative,
the rectified linear
activation function is
going to clip it, and
it's just going to be a 0.
And then when we go to create a
probability distribution from that,
it will always be 0, whether it was a
negative 20 or negative 9,000.
And then the other problem is, what if
all of the values are in the negatives?
There would be impossible to learn from
here, and again, we haven't quite yet
reached back propagation, but learning
from clipped values, quote unquote,
how wrong or how right is something,
is very difficult because there is no
meaning once you've clipped, you've lost
all meaning.
Was it a negative 20 before it got
clipped, or was it a negative 1 million?
We don't know.
So then you might suggest, let's just use
a linear activation function.
Let's basically do nothing.
The problem is, you're
still going to need to figure
out what the heck do you
do with these negative values.
So you might throw
your hands up at this point
and be like, let's just
use absolute values.
Or let's square the
output, then we'll just
solve this whole negative
problem altogether.
The problem with this
is, after you have these
values, you need to be
able to back propagate.
You need to be able to have an optimizer
intelligently optimize your variables.
Well, if you have a
negative 9 that got absolute
value to a 9, that's a big
difference than a 9, right?
So the variables that you would need to
tweak and the directions that you would
need to tweak these variables to get those
changes that you want would vary.
So, we can't just lose the meaning.
A negative 9 is not the same as a positive
9.
So, what the heck do we do?
Enter exponentiation.
So the exponential function is y or your
output is equal to e, or Euler's number,
raised to the power of x, which is your
input.
Euler's number is approximately 2.71828
and so on.
And exponentiation is the act of applying
the exponential function to some value.
So, what this does for us is it solves our
negatives issue by making sure no
negative, or really no
value, can be negative
at the output of the
exponential function.
And it does this while not tossing away the
value or the meaning of that negativity.
It's still on a scale, let's say.
So, the exponentiation of 1.1 is 3 or 3 in
some change.
The exponentiation of negative 1.1 is
0.3329 or so.
So, this is more than just using absolute
values or squaring the value, for example.
Now, also, in theory, you don't have to
use Euler's number here, and you would
still solve all your problems up to this
point.
But Euler's number is actually
going to be coming handy later
on, and we'll be sure to
reference that when we get there.
But this is how we're solving this problem
of negativity.
Alright, getting back
to our code, let's code
the raw Python implementation
for exponentiation.
So, to do this, we're just going to keep
the original layer outputs.
And first, we need
a definition for E, the
constant Euler's number,
and that is 2.7182846.
I hope I got that right.
Also, if you are in Python, you can always
import math, and then rather than hard
coding Euler's number that way,
you could say E equals math.E.
And that would be the same thing.
But if they are following along in some
other language, and you don't have that
kind of math library
that just gives you the
number, you could just
hard code it in that way.
So, once we have that number, we want to
exponentiate all each of these values.
So, doing that is really basic Python
here.
So, we're going to say X values,
we're going to make that an empty list.
And then we're just going to iterate over
layer outputs.
So, for output in layer outputs, we're
going to X values dot append E to the power.
..
Actually, it's capital E to the power of
whatever that output is.
And then when we're all done, we can print
X values.
Let's go ahead and run that.
And we have our
exponentiated values at this point,
checking the book to
make sure it is identical.
And it looks like it is.
Okay, great.
So, that's exponentiation.
Really, not much to it at that point.
So, the next step, once we've exponentiated
these values, is to normalize the values.
So, what do we mean by normalize the
values?
So, in our case, it's going to be a single
output neurons value, divided by the sum
of all of the other output neurons in that
output layer.
And this gives us the probability
distribution that we want.
But we still want to exponentiate
before this point, because
again, we need to get rid of
all of these negative values.
But we do not want to lose the meaning of
the negative value.
So, we're exponentiating to
convert negatives to positives
without actually losing the
meaning of a negative value.
So, continuing along in our
raw Python implementation
here, let's go ahead
and code in normalization.
So, again, normalization occurs
after we've done exponentiation,
which will rid us of these
pesky negative values.
So, to do the normalization,
again, it's a single
value divided by the
total of all the values.
So, we've got exponential values.
So, what we're going to say is norm base
equals the sum of those exponential values.
And then we're going to say norm values.
That was, yeah.
We're going to do norm values dot append.
And it's just going to be that value
divided by the norm base.
And this will give us the normalized
value.
So, we can print norm values.
And then also, this
should add up, it should
add up to one, or
very, very close to one.
So, print a sum of norm values.
We'll run that.
And what we get is here is our probability
distribution.
So, this first, this first kind of list
here, this is our exponentiated values.
Then this is our normalized exponentiated
values.
And then this just sums it up and shows
that it does indeed add up to basically one.
Those values should be pretty close to
what's in the book.
It actually isn't exactly, but this isn't
using NumPy.
So, the values should line up,
I think, when we're using NumPy.
We'll confirm that when we get there.
So, the n and fs, first of all, we're not
even initializing the n and fs package.
But that is part of what the init package
is doing.
But here, interestingly
enough, even raw
Python seems to vary
from machine to machine.
I don't think it actually matters at this
stage.
So, they're close, but
it's like as you get to some
of these ladder decimals,
that's where it's differing.
So, that's the raw Python implementation.
And again, if you're coming
from some other language,
you would need to implement
this in your language.
But now the next thing that we're going to
do is convert this to NumPy.
So, what we're going
to do is take, I guess,
in our code, we
probably are retaining e.
But we can keep math.e there, outputs
there.
We're going to go ahead and import NumPy
as np.
And rather than doing, really, all of this,
we delete, and x values just becomes np.
x.
And what are we applying this exponential
function to?
Layer outputs.
So, by default, typically, NumPy
functions, what they're going to do is,
first, they will just by default,
impact every value.
And if you want it to be in a little bit
more specific way, you can become more
specific, and we'll actually be showing
that very shortly.
But by default, if you just do this, it's
going to apply this to each value in total.
So, that's a quicker way to get our
exponential values.
And then for the normalization values,
all we need to do at this point is,
we're just going to say, norm
underscore values is equal
to the x values divided by
the np.sum of the x values.
So, let's go ahead and run that real
quick, and then we see that we do indeed
still get the same value or same ish
values.
And this time, it actually does line up
with what's in the book, but if you wanted
to be super particular, I would imagine,
we would import nnfs and nnfs.in it.
These values actually
do line up with what is in
the book, but let's just
run that one more time.
And so, if you did have any variance
there, hopefully that would change it.
So, okay, so that lines up exactly.
And as you can see, it's a little shorter
code.
I think it's a little more legible.
But, yeah, so that is our exponentiation
and then our normalization.
So, to sum up everything up to this point
for our coding of the softmax activation
function, we have input, right,
which is actually going to be the output
layer of data that we're going to input
into this activation function.
We exponentiate those input values,
so each one uniquely gets exponentiated,
then we normalize, and then that becomes
our output.
So, the combination of this exponentiation
and normalization is what makes up the
softmax activation function, the formula
for which is this.
And hopefully this formula is actually
pretty simple to understand at this point,
since you've already
seen the code that goes into
it, and it's not really
complicated in any way.
Okay, so at this point, we know everything
that goes into the softmax activation
function, and now it is just a function of
actually applying and implementing this in
such a way that makes sense for our actual
neural network applications.
So, the main issue that we have at this
stage is we are currently working with a
single kind of vector here of a layer's
outputs.
When really, we're not going to have a
single layer of outputs, we're actually
not going to have a single output from a
layer.
We're going to have a batch of these
outputs, because we're going to have a
batch of inputs, and that's going to
produce a batch of outputs.
So, the next thing we want to do is
convert this, and really all this,
to work as a batch.
So to do that, first let's make this an
actual batch.
And again, I am going to use the same
values that we have in the book.
So, let me paste and paste.
And the second output
here is an 8.9 negative 1.81
0.2, and then down here
we get a 1.41 1.0510.026.
Okay.
Also, we can kind of clean up here.
I just realized if we still
have math and math.e, we
don't need that anymore,
because this handles it for us.
So, how do we convert to batch?
So for exponentiating, it turns out we
don't actually need to do anything,
because these NumPy functions here work by
default at the individual value level.
So, if we print x
values, I thought I did, I
thought I already completed
that, I guess I didn't.
There we have our values.
It's actually already done for us,
and it's correct.
So, the next question is, okay,
how do we do this step?
So, x values, we don't need to change
anything there for a batch, but for some,
we do.
So, to illustrate sum, rather than doing
the sum of the exponential values,
it's kind of hard to visually add these
up.
We're going to do the sum of... let's do
this.
I'm just going to comment these out.
We are going to... let's just print np.sum
layer outputs.
Now, remember, what do we want to do here?
We actually want to iterate over here,
over this 2D matrix.
We want to iterate over this, and do this
sum, this sum, this sum, and this sum.
But by default, I already told you,
it's going to do as individual values.
So by default, what we get is a single
scalar value.
That's not what we wanted.
We really want three values.
For sure, we want three values.
So, how do we get those three values?
So, the first order of business is to pass
the axes parameter here.
So, we're going to say axes.
And the axes, by default, is actually
none.
And that gives us the same value that we
saw before.
Ax is zero.
To put it extremely simply on a 2D matrix,
it's going to be the sum of columns.
So, we're going to run this again.
And as you can see, 15.11 is this column,
and then 0.451 is this column, and 2.
611 is this last column.
Unfortunately, that's not what we want.
We actually want the sum of the rows put
simply.
So, we can change that to axes one.
And sure enough, what we get is what we
hoped for, which is the sum here,
here, and here.
Now, we still have a slight problem.
What are we trying to do with this sum?
Well, it turns out we're
trying to take these
exponential values,
which has this shape.
It is a matrix.
And we're attempting to divide it by what
we do the sum operation with.
And we don't actually want to just
willy-nilly divide it.
It's really important that things line up.
So, it's for the same reason that we want
to make sure values are lining up when we
do the dot product, and when we're doing
like a matrix product, right?
So, even though NP dot dot, it is a dot
product with vectors, but it's also doing
a matrix product for us, we need those
values to line up.
So, we do a transpose, right?
For that same reason, we need the right
values to line up here.
Right now, if we did this, it's not going
to actually be dividing what we want
exponentials to be divided by,
right?
So, what we want to do is we need to shape
this correctly.
And we could reshape this, but we can also
just simply use keep-dems.
So, keep-is it keep-dems?
Yeah, all one word.
And then true, run that.
And now, it is a matrix
of the exact same- I
hate to say shape, but
it's the same orientation.
It's the same dimensions, okay?
So, it's just a sum.
So now, it is literally this right here.
It's just the sum of
these values, the sum of
these values, and then
the sum of these values.
So, with that, what we can do is we can
say the norm values is exponential values
divided by the sum of exponential values at
axes one, and then keep-dems equals true.
We get rid of this row here, and now we
have print norm values.
We run that, and now we have our actual
normalized values.
So, from this point, we really have one
more thing, and I think we'll cover it
here, is one problem
that we have up to this
point is with specifically
exponential values.
So, there's one thing that we
want to change with exponential
values before we convert
this to our actual class object.
So, with that, let us
go ahead and talk about
what we're going to do
with exponential values.
One slight issue with
exponentiation is the explosion of
values as the input to the
exponential function grows.
It doesn't take much to get massive
numbers, and even worse, it doesn't take
too long to reach an overflow.
So, one way to combat this overflow is to
take all of the values in this output
layer prior to exponentiation,
and subtract the largest value in that
layer from all of the values in that
layer.
And what this causes is
now the largest value will be a
zero, and everything else
is going to be less than zero.
Now, because the largest value prior to
exponentiation is actually a zero,
our range of possibilities becomes
somewhere between zero and one after
exponentiation, because the exponentiation
of zero equals one.
So, this means our range of
values can only be between
zero and one, thus no more
worrying about overflowing.
So, the final concern that you might have
is what sort of impact does subtracting
the max value from
everything have on the actual
output of the softmax
activation function.
So, all other things being equal and
assuming that we don't have some sort of
overflow error, if we have two output
layers and one we don't subtract the max
from and one we do, after we do our
exponentiation and our normalization,
the actual output is identically the same.
The only thing we've done is protected
ourselves from an actual overflow error.
Alright, so with the subtraction of the
max value in mind, we are going to now go
to the code that we left
off on with part five and
we're going to add our
softmax activation class.
And then we're going to implement it here
as well as change things here.
I've used different variable names and
stuff like that.
So, I'm going to
attempt to convert this to
be exactly what we
have in the book as well.
And so, by doing that
we'll also be able to
finally test the softmax
activation function.
So, these are the changes that we want to
make.
So, first off, we're going to be
redefining this data.
So, I'm actually going to delete these.
Then, we'll just add this underneath the
value activation function.
And we're going to say class activation,
activation underscore softmax.
And then we're going to define the forward
method, again, self-inputs.
And now we're just going to implement the
code that we've talked about and covered
already up to this
point, except for the max
thing, but I'm going to
show you that in a moment.
So, the exponential underscore values is
going to be equal to np dot x of inputs.
And then we want to minus the np dot max.
And immediately alarm bells should be sort
of going off.
And that is, if we run
np dot max, and we, for
example, we're going
to say np dot max inputs.
And also, while we're here, what is
inputs?
So, up to this point, inputs, in this
case, because we're using the softmax
activation function for the activation
function of an output layer, inputs are
actually the outputs so far of our model,
right?
And so, again, we've
got these outputs, and
those outputs are
going to be in batch form.
So, there will be a batch of these
outputs.
So, if we just said np dot max of inputs,
which would be np dot max of a batch of
outputs, up to this point, it's going to be
the highest value of all of those values.
Now, you'd probably get away with it.
I think it would probably work,
but it would be a mistake.
It would work, but not as well as it
should.
So, instead of what you want to say is np
dot max inputs of, and immediately you
should already know where
we're headed, it's going to
be of axes one, and then,
again, keep dems will be true.
So, we're going to take inputs,
which is going to be this batch of inputs.
And, again, we want to subtract
the max along of axes one,
and then we want to keep that
dimension, right, of that array.
So, once we've done that, we now have our
exponential values of a batch,
and we are subtracting the max along the
way.
Again, so we just don't hit an overflow
value.
The actual outputs will be exactly the
same after we normalize all that.
So, we're not really losing anything by
doing this.
We're just preventing an overflow.
So, exponential values is done.
Now we're going to say probability is
going to be equal to x values divided by
np dot sum of the
exponential values of axes
one, axes one, keep
dems is going to be true.
And, again, we've already actually... this
we've already covered, but again,
we're trying to sum each of the rows,
and we want to keep the dimension.
So, finally, we're going
to define our self dot
output, and that is going
to be the probabilities.
Okay.
So, that's our soft max activation
function, and now what I want to make sure
I do is I use the exact same layer values
and so on so.
We already got rid of the code up above,
I think.
I think what I'll do... I think we'll just
code it from scratch here.
So, here is our framework up to this
point.
Well, first thing we're going to do is
define our data.
So, x, y is going to be equal to spiral
data, and then we're going to say samples.
How many samples do we want to have?
We're going to say 100 per class,
and we're going to say classes.
We're going to have three separate
classes.
Now, what we're going to do is we're going
to say dense one is equal to layer,
dense, and the shape here is going to be
two, and then three.
So, we only have two input features.
Again, spiral data is just x, y data,
so it's just coordinates.
So, the input here is going to be x,
y, that's two, so the input must be two.
Now, the output could be anything you
want.
You could say 90 if you wanted,
but we're going to say three
because we're going to
follow, we're going to say three.
Because we're going to follow the book.
Now, after we've got dense one,
we're going to define also activation one,
and that will be an activation value.
And then we're going to define dense two
is going to be another layer dense.
It, the input, because
the output of the previous
layer was a three, the
input must be three.
Now, the output could
be anything we want, but
we're going to treat this
like it's an output layer.
So, how many neurons should this output
layer have?
Well, we have three classes, so we're
going to say three.
So, dense two is defined,
and then we're going to say
activation, activation two is
going to be an activation softmax.
And then now, we're going to begin passing
data actually through here.
So, we're going to say dense one,
dense one dot forward, and we're going to
forward our actual input data here.
Then, we need to activate it.
So, activation one dot forward,
dense one dot output.
Then, we're going to pass that through
dense two.
So, we're going to say dense two dot
forward, activation one dot output.
And then, activation two dot forward the
output from dense two.
And, at this point, because
we do the forward, we now
have the output, which is
going to be probabilities.
So, for example, we can print activation
two dot output, and let's just do the,
there should be three hundred of them.
So, we're going to just do the first five.
Let's go ahead and run that.
And, what we get is, again, this is a
batch.
Okay, so we passed all of them at the same
time, in this case.
So, we, theory, had a batch of three
hundred.
Now, each of these is unique.
So, this is a sample.
So, this had an input
of two values, and this
is each neuron value
of those two values.
And, it just continues to repeat,
and then this is just the first five.
Now, it should be no surprise.
Everything was initialized randomly.
So, it turns out that the distribution of
predictions is indeed random.
It's a perfect, you know, not a perfect,
but very close to a perfect one-third
prediction for everything.
This is totally normal.
When you randomly initialize a model,
that's kind of what you expect.
So, now what we need to do is actually
train this model.
Because, like, for
example, let's see if any
of these are obviously
bigger than the others.
Three, three, three, five.
So, in this case, right, if we did an
argmax on this right here, this class,
you know, of index two, is the largest,
unless I'm missing something, but anyways,
it is the largest it looks like.
So, that would be the prediction,
and maybe that would be accurate.
Maybe that would be correct.
But instead, what we
want to really do is we
don't want to know just
what's right and wrong.
We want to know how
right and how wrong, and
to calculate that, we
use a loss function.
And that is the topic of the next video.
So, if you've got any
questions, comments, concerns,
whatever, up to this point,
we kind of covered a lot.
But I think the Softmax activation function
is relatively simplistic to pick up.
But if you have questions,
comments, concerns,
whatever, feel free
to leave those below.
Again, the physical versions of the books
are done.
As are obviously the e-book and all that.
It's ready to be downloaded and consumed.
So, if you want something to follow along
with the videos, or you want to kind of
refresh from the videos, or read before
the video, watch the video, that kind of
stuff, definitely check that out at nnfs
.io.
Otherwise, I will see you guys in another
video.